Now, the American Revolution didn't just
happen because the colonists were having
feelings about Big Mama Britain's
increasingly oppressive policies. No,
there was a whole set of revolutionary
ideas swirling around their thinkythinky
parts that taken together became a
significant cause for the independence
movement. And I reckon we ought to talk
about it. So, if you're ready to get
them brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay. Now, right at the beginning, I
need to remind you that even as late as
1775, independence from Great Britain
was not the main desire of the American
colonist. Mainly they wanted to remain
British subjects, but they wanted their
imperial parent to stop dumping all over
their rights as British subjects.
However, in the short span of time
between the end of the French and Indian
War and the beginning of the American
Revolution, certain ideas began to
change some of the colonist views on the
relationship between the government and
the people. And once these ideas became
firmly planted in the colonial
imagination, independence started to
seem like the only way forward. Oh, and
by the way, if you want note guys to
follow along with this video and all my
videos, check that link in the
description. Anyway, it's high time we
looked at these revolutionary ideas
square in the face. And we're going to
break into three categories. First, the
colonists embraced a big surprise,
enlightenment ideas. But before we
explore some of those ideas
individually, you have to understand the
context. You see, the Enlightenment was
first of all a European movement. And
lots of Europeans embraced these ideas
as well. But even so, no European state
experienced revolution on account of
these ideas with the possible exception
of the English Civil War. But the
colonies in North America were
different. You see, for the most part,
those who migrated to the North American
colonies were able to build a new
society from scratch. And that way,
without the heavy weight of centuries of
social tradition like they had in
Europe, the new world was kind of an
experimental laboratory for new ways of
thinking and living. Therefore, it is
not surprising that new ideas about
government and the nature of human
beings developed by enlightenment
thinkers found eager adopters in this
part of the world. And that those ideas
created fertile soil for a political
revolution. Anyway, let's sit a spell
with a few of the most potent
enlightenment ideas that animated the
American Revolution. First was the
elevation of the individual. In other
words, enlightenment thinkers emphasized
that the most basic element of society
was the individual human, not collective
groups. Second was the idea of natural
rights. Thinkers like John Lockach argue
that every individual human was born
with certain rights that came from God.
Rights like life, liberty, and property.
That my dear pupil is an explosive idea
because the implication is that if human
rights come from God then they do not in
fact come from a monarch. And that
further means that if natural rights are
granted by the dang almighty then
monarchs who are not the almighty have
no business infringing on those rights.
And then related to that is the third
enlightenment idea you need to know,
namely the social contract. And this is
very timely at this point in the video
because I'm sure you're wondering,
>> but Heimler, if rights do come from God
and a monarch does infringe upon them,
then what?
>> Well, that's where the social contract
comes in, baby. So thinkers like Lockach
and Jean Jacqu Rouso developed the idea
that human societies made up of
individuals endowed with natural rights
must construct governments of their own
will and that the main purpose of that
government is to protect their natural
rights. In other words, the power to
govern is actually in the hands of the
people and they agree to give up certain
freedoms in exchange for government
protection of their rights and security.
And that means that if the government
becomes a tyrannical turd, thus
violating the contract, then the people
have the right to overthrow that
government and replace it with a new
one. And compared to the reigning view
of government power, namely the divine
right of kings, which basically said
that God establishes monarchs, so you
know, do whatever they say. This was a
significant departure. Okay. Now, more
briefly, let's consider a second set of
ideas that played a role in the
independence movement, namely political
ideas from the radical wigs, who were a
group of British political theorists.
So, educated colonists with a penchant
for thinkythinky stuff got an earful of
radical wigish ideas, which really all
came down to this. They warned against
political corruption and the danger of
tyranny that comes from the arbitrary
power of monarchs and aristocrats. And
by arbitrary power, they meant power
that was hereditary or handed down
through families. In that scheme, power
was given to the people born in the
right family, even if they were dumber
than a box of rocks. And so these ideas
along with several others deeply shaped
the American imagination about society
and politics and led them to emphasize
individual talent above hereditary
privilege. And finally, the third
category of revolutionary ideas were
religious in nature. You see, the
effects of the first great awakening
still lingered in the American
population, which among other things had
greatly increased the nation's religious
identity and fervor. And this had two
effects. First, many colonists who had
been influenced by this movement
perceived the relative liberty they
enjoyed in the American colonies as a
gift from God. Second, with the
awakening's emphasis on the authority of
individual religious experience over
against submitting to formal church
hierarchies, they had learned to treat
systems of authority with suspicion.
Therefore, as British policies became
more and more oppressive, the widespread
adoption of these ideas made many
colonists exceedingly wary of any
perceived threat to their rights. And
so, now we begin to see the colonists
change their minds about the notion of
independence over the course of a few
years. And there were several
ingredients in that independent stew.
First was the convening of the first
continental congress in 1774 in
Philadelphia, which was called in
response to the passage of the
intolerable acts, which we talked about
in the last video. Their goal was to
create a united plan to resist further
violations of their rights, which in
their mind were still British rights.
And so among other things, the Congress
encouraged colonists to continue
boycotting British goods. But the point
to remember here is that the meeting of
the Congress centralized resistance to
British policies rather than relying on
weaker, more localized resistance. And
then the second ingredient was actual
armed conflict. So by 1775, fighting had
erupted between British soldiers and
colonial people in Boston and eight
colonists had died. These fights in
Lexington and conquered and the
additional conflict in the battle of
Bunker Hill led the colonist to convene
the second continental congress. And
this body served as a provisional
government that organized the colonial
response to British aggression. And in
this series of meetings which built off
a petition of grievances outlined in the
first Continental Congress, some
delegates argued for negotiation with
Britain in order to reestablish a proper
colonial relationship with their rights
intact. To that end, Congress issued the
olive branch petition, which appealed
directly to King George III to avoid a
full-blown war and reestablish colonial
rights, which is to say the fullness of
their British rights. But others like
Patrick Henry argued loudly that the
British actions had indeed revealed
their turd hood and therefore what was
needed was a movement for independence.
But even so, those who called for
independence were still a minority among
the colonists. So what changed? Well,
what changed was in fact the third
ingredient, namely the publication of a
pamphlet called common sense by Thomas
Payne. So after the petitions sent by
the Continental Congress to the king
asking for peace were rejected, colonial
resentment reached its peak. And right
as that resentment stew reached a boil,
Thomas Payne seemed to put words to what
the colonist had felt but so far had
been unable to articulate. And basically
the common sense of common sense was
that independence from Great Britain was
the only way forward. And once it was
published, this pamphlet sold like mad
across the colonies. But of special
importance was the kind of arguments
Payne used to make his case. First, he
made abundant use of enlightenment ideas
like natural rights and social contract
and republicanism to demonstrate that
Britain's behavior of late amounted to
nothing short of tyranny. Second, Payne
also made use of biblical arguments,
most notably the development of the
monarchy in the Old Testament and how
God considered it a sin. Additionally,
he combined anti- monarchical ideas with
calls for popular support of the
revolution by appealing to common
people. And given how deeply the
colonists had been shaped by the
Enlightenment and biblical thought, this
pamphlet convinced a lot of folks. And
so by 1776, the actions of the British
and the wide diffusion of these ideas
led to a formal declaration of
independence penned by Thomas Jefferson
with editorial help from John Adams and
Benjamin Franklin. And it's going to be
important for you to remember that
Jefferson didn't just think this whole
document up with his own magnificent
brain. No, he based the ideas of the
Declaration off of dozens of state and
local declarations, not least the
Virginia Declaration of Rights. All of
which, when taken together, revealed the
unique expression of the American mind.
Anyway, the purpose of the Declaration
was to affect the formal separation of
the colonies from British rule. And as
you may have guessed by now, the way
Jefferson did that was by making liberal
use of enlightenment ideas like the
social contract and natural rights.
Okay, click here to watch my other
videos for unit 3 and you can click here
to grab my video note guides which are
going to help you cram all the contents
of this course firmly into your brain
folders. I appreciate you coming around
and I'll catch you on the flipflop.